Guide to the Hal Sirowitz Papers MSS.196
Fales Library and Special Collections
Hal Sirowitz Papers
1943-2004
1990-2001
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sirowitz, Hal
MSS.196
17 Linear Feet in 13 record cartons; 3 manuscript boxes; 2 half manuscript boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, 1 oversize folder, and 1 CD box
5 audiocassettes
6 videocassettes (vhs)
16 sound discs (cd)
1 electronic discs (cd-rom)
Hal Sirowitz (born 1949), known as "the people's poet," is an internationally known American poet, author, and retired public school teacher. He is most known for his work, Mother Said, and was a frequent competitor in Nuyorican Poets Café's Friday Night Poetry Slam in the late 1980s and early 1990s. In 1994, Sirowitz was awarded a National Endowment for the Arts Fellowship and in 2004, a New York Foundation for the Arts fellowship. He became the second Poet Laureate of Queens, New York, a position he held for three years. In 2012, he was the co-winner of the Noir Con Poetry Contest. Sirowitz taught special education classes in the New York City public school system for twenty-three years. This collection dates between 1943 and 2002 (bulk 1990-2001) and consists of materials reflecting his career as a writer and public school teacher. Materials include print publications; original manuscripts; poems; plays; academic writings, clippings; teaching materials; newsletters; postcards; ephemera; photographs; receipts, address lists; author bios; correspondence; promotional materials and sales records; works by other authors; an award plaque; notebooks; an MTA Subway poster; and audiovisual materials documenting the spoken word.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open witout restsrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchasaed from Hal Sirowitz in 2007; additional materials were donated by Sirowitz in 2010. The accession numbers related to this collection are 2007.196 and 2010.196.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged by subject.
Biographical / Historical
Hal Sirowitz (born 1949), known as "the people's poet," is an internationally known American poet, author, and retired public school teacher. Sirowitz first began to attract attention at the Nuyorican Poets Café Friday Night Poetry Slam in the late 1980's and early 1990's. He was on the 1993 Nuyorican Poetry Slam Team which competed in that year's National Poetry Slam in San Francisco. He has performed his poetry across the country and Europe and is known as the most popular translated poet in the history of Norway, where animated films and a play based on his poetry have been adapted. In 2007, he was a participant in the Jerusalem Conference of Writers and Poets. Sirowitz has performed and appeared on MTV's Spoken Word Unplugged; Lollapalooza; several international poetry festivals and public television programs; the Saint Mark's Church New Year's Day Poetry Marathon, NPR's All Things Considered and Fresh Air with Terry Gross; and PBS's Poetry Heaven and the United States of Poetry. He was awarded a National Endowment for the Arts Fellowship in 1994 and a New York Foundation for the Arts fellowship in 2004. In 2000, Sirowitz became the second Poet Laureate of Queens, New York, a position he held for three years. In 2012, he was the co-winner of the Noir Con Poetry Contest judged by Robert Polito. Sirowitz taught special education classes in the New York City public school system for twenty-three years.
Source: http://www.halsirowitz.com/
Custodial History
Materials were purchased from Hal Sirowitz in 2007. In 2010 Sirowtiz moved from New York to Philadelphia and sent one large envelope of materials to Ron Kolm to be delivered to NYU and added to the collection.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Materials
Gathering of the Tribes Archive (MSS 198)
Bob Holman Audio/Video Poetry Collection (MSS 128)
Ron Kolm Papers (MSS 079)
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials created and collected by Hal Sirowitz that document his career as an American poet, author, and educator with the bulk of the materials documenting his writing career. Materials include print publications; original manuscripts; poems; plays; academic writings; clippings; teaching materials; newsletters; postcards; ephemera; photographs; receipts, address lists; author bios; correspondence; promotional materials and sales records; works by other authors; an award plaque; notebooks; an MTA Subway poster; 6 VHS tapes; 16 commercial CDs; 1 CDR; and 5 cassette tapes. The print publications from Sirowitz's personal library include magazines, literary journals, and books that he subscribed to or feature his works and works of his peers that he collected between 1974 and 2004.
Separated Materials
Two folders of student papers and one folder of financial records were removed for deaccession.
American poetry -- 20th century.; American poetry -- 21st century; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Authors, American -- 21st century.; Teaching -- United States; Teaching students with special needs; Correspondence.; Poems.; Manuscripts (documents); Publications (documents); Sound recordings.; Video recordings.; Clippings (information artifacts); Notebooks; Awards; Sirowitz, Hal
- Academic Writing, 1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- At War Against Her Teeth, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Awards, 1982, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- "The Back Up" by Bonnie Walker, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Big Fish: Council of All Beginnings Issue, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Big Fish: Hal Sirowitz Tribute Issue, 1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Changing the Color of Her Lipstick: A Play", undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Civil Service Rating for Estelle Vogel, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Clippings, 1993-2000 (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
- A Collection of Short Plays, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Contacts, 1995-2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
- Correspondence, personal, 1979-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 18-26)
- Correspondence, professional, 1984-2003, undated (Box 1, Folder 27-36)
- Curiculum vitae, author bios, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Damaged Body: poems, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Deformed Finger, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Direct Mail, 1991-2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
- "Disloyal to the Tribe: A Play", undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Dodge Poetry Festival, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "A Dog's Heart", undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "Down with Rogers", undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Father Said, circa 2004 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
- Finding Your Way Back Home, undated (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
- First Night Morris, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Flyers, invitations, and ephemera, 1990-2001 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Flyers, invitations, etc., 1983-2002, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-19)
- "Former Lovers and the Ones In Between", undated (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
- Freeman, Dan, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- "Getting to Know Each Other, My Dead Goldfish" with Blair Wilson, circa 1992 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- A Gradual Period of Disenchantment, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Grant and Residency Applications, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Hal Almost Said, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Hal Almost Said: A Memoir, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Hal Almost Said, undated (Box 2, Folder 28-47, Box 3, Folder 1-4)
- Hal Almost Said: front matter and chapter one, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Hal Almost Said: chapter one, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Hal Almost Said: chapter two, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Hal Almost Said: chapter three, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Hal Almost Said: chapter four, undated (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
- Hal Almost Said: chapter five, undated (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
- Hal Almost Said: chapter six, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Hal Almost Said: chapter eight, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Hal Almost Said: fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Hal Almost Said: A Memoir, undated (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
- Hal Almost Said, "Mother Said", undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Hal Said: A Memoir, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Happy Baby, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
- He Said, She Said, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Helsinki Festival, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Home Remedy, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
- I Liked You Better When You Were a Wolf, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
- "I Said" III, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Manuscripts, 1978-1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 28-37, Box 4, Folder 1-30, Box 5, Folder 1-26)
- Manuscripts by others, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Meeting A Mysterious Friend, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Messages and memoranda, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Mother Also Said, 1996, undated (Box 5, Folder 30-31)
- Mother Said, 1996, undated (Box 5, Folder 32-34)
- Mother Said II, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Mother Said: film treatment, 1999, undated (Box 5, Folder 36-37)
- Mother Said: Finland tour, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 38)
- Mother Said: Norwegian stage adaptation, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Mother Said: proofs, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Mother Said: Spanish translations, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Mother Said: tour, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Mother Said: tour, west coast, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- My Therapist Said, circa 1998 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- My Therapist Said: additional therapy poems, undated (Box 6, Folder 7-9)
- My Therapist Said: tour, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- National Poetry Slam Championship, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- New Manuscript, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
- The Next Ancient World by Jennifer Michael Hecht, circa 2001 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Notebook, 1986-2000, undated (Box 6, Folder 14-34)
- Olso tour, undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Performance notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
- Personal effects, undated (Box 6, Folder 37)
- Personal materials, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 38)
- Photographs, 1997, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
- Poems by Mia Hansford, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Poet Laureate of Queens Award, 1997-2001 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Poets Against War, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Poet's House: "Friends in the House", 1997 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Promotional materials, 1989-2000, undated (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
- Promotional writing, 1993, 1997, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Prose poems, 2000, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Racing to Oblivion poems, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Receipts, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Sales records, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- The Same Blood, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Searching at the Door: A Play, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Sitting Around While the Neighbors are Fighting: A Play, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Softic, Tanja, 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Teaching Materials, 1987-1996, undated (Box 7, Folder 17-19)
- These Are My Parents, and This Is My Girl, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Tobin, Juanita, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Torrez, Juliette, 1996, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Travel documentation, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Two-Ton Santa, Issue 97, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 24)
- An Unbearable Assembling, Number Two, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 25)
- Voices of Queens Festival, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 26)
- The Waiting Room Was Empty: A Play, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
- War Against Slime, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
- We Could Have Been Better Dance Partners, undated (Box 7, Folder 29-30)
- When Mother Stopped Speaking: A Memoir, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 31)
- When Sex Gets Mixed Up With Love, undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
- Why Sparrow Should Be President, circa 1992 (Box 7, Folder 33)
- Wilson, Blair, 1992-1997, undated (Box 7, Folder 34-35)
- Clippings, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 36)
- Correspondence: personal, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 37)
- Correspondence: professional, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 38)
- Direct Mail, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 39)
- Ephemera, 1982-2001, undated (Box 7, Folder 40-41)
- Kupferberg, Tuli, undated (Box 7, Folder 42)
- Manuscripts, undated (Box 7, Folder 43)
- Promotional materials, 1982-2001, undated (Box 7, Folder 44)
- Sales records, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 45)
- Submission research, 1986, undated (Box 7, Folder 46)
- Writings: unidentified authors, 2001, undated (Box 7, Folder 47)
- "I Finally Managed to Speak to Her", 1998 (Folder 7)
  Scope and Contents
  From the New York City Metropolitan Transit Authority "Poetry in Motion" series.
- Cover, 1986-10-1993-05 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Clippings, 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Avenue E, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Exquisite Corpse, 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Wallpaper Magazine, 1985-1991 (Box 8, Folder 5-7)
- Photographic print by Bob Witz, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Correspondence: personal, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Downtown, 1986-1994 (Box 9, Folder 1-5, Box 10, Folder 1-4)
- Clippings, 1982-2002 (Box 11, Folder 1-4, Box 12, Folder 1-3)
- Poetry readings and plays [audiocassettes], undated (Box 13, Folder 1-5)
- Poetry readings and plays [VHS], undated (Box 13, Folder 6-11)
- Poetry and music [CDs], undated (Box Shared Fales 007, Folder 1-17)
- Print publications, 1974-2004 (Box 14, Box 15, Folder 1-4, Box 16, Folder 1-2, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20, Box 21)